Lothar Wolff collection, 1926-1987
George Eastman Museum
Subseries 16,The 13 Clocks,1950-1951,1958-1969,undated
Subseries 17,The TV Bible,1980-1985,undated
Subseries 18,Wild, Wild World of Animals,1973-1975
Subseries 19,Windjammer: The Voyage of the Christian Radich,1957-1958
Subseries 20,The World We Live In[aka Life Around Us],1968-1974,1981-1986,undated
Sub-subseries 1, General,1968-1974,undated
Sub-subseries 2, "The Not-So-Solid Earth,"1971-1972,undated
Sub-subseries 3, "Rock-a-Bye Baby,"1971-1972,1981-1986
Subseries 21, Miscellaneous,ca. 1932,1938,1948-1967,1973-1986,undated
Series 3, General Research Materials,1947,1957,1967,1972-1985,undated
Series 4, Festivals/Retrospectives,1975-1986
Series 5, Publications/Clippings,1932-1946,1951-1984
Series 6, Personal Records,1926-1940,1946,1968-1972,1984-1985,undated
Series 7, Photographs,1927-1984,undated
Series 8, Film/Video,1943-1953,1960-1961,1966-1986
Subseries 1,Coast Guard Films,1944,undated
Subseries 2,The Earth and Its Peoples,1948-1949
Subseries 3,The March of Time,1943,1947
Subseries 4,Other People, Other Places 1974
Subseries 5,Planet Earth,1960-1961
Subseries 6,The Sun and the Earth,ca. 1966
Subseries 7,Wild, Wild World of Animals,ca. 1973
Subseries 8,The World We Live In,1968-1973
Subseries 9, Features and Other Non-series Films,1953,1961,1978-1986,undated
Series 9, Artwork,approximately 1960-1987,undated
Series 10, Awards/Citations,1961-1962,1965-1966,1971-1972,1980-1982
Beatty, Warren, 1937-; Blessed, Brian; Brooks, Louise, 1906-1985; Casals, Pablo, 1876-1973; Crowther, Bosley; Danois, Jacques; De Rochemont, Louis, 1899-1978; Fejos, Paul, 1897-1963; Guiles, Fred Lawrence; Guinness, Alec, 1914-2000; Hitchens, Gordon; Lamač, Karel, 1898-1952; Lang, Fritz, 1890-1976; Lee, Robert E. A. (Robert Edward Alexander), 1921-2009; Leigh, Vivien, 1913-1967; Meier, Theo, 1908-1982; Ondra, Anny; Pabst, G. W. (Georg Wilhelm), 1885-1967; Paris, Barry; Prescott, James W.; Shute, James L.; St. John, Jill; Stapp, Philip; Thurber, James, 1894-1961; Wolff, Lothar; Wolff, Violet M.
United States. Economic Cooperation Administration; Hom-AG für Filmfabrikation; Kitt Peak National Observatory; Lothar Wolff Productions; Louis De Rochemont Associates; Lutheran Film Associates; March of time (Motion Picture); March of Time, Inc.; Marshall Plan; National Geographic Society (U.S.); National Geographic Films; National Geographic Society (U.S.). Educational Media Department; Ondra-Lamač Film; Parufamet; Les Films Osso; Time, Inc.; Time-Life Films; United States. Economic Cooperation Administration--Films.
Astronomy--Films.; Ballooning--History.; Composers in motion pictures; Educational films.; Ethnographic films.; Human geography--Films.; International Geophysical Year, 1957-1958.; Motion picture industry--Public relations; Motion pictures--Editing.; Motion pictures--Production and direction.Newsreels.; Newsreels.; Religious films.; Science films.; Wildlife films.
acetate film; animation cells; awards; black-and-white negatives; black-and-white photographs; booklets; brochures; bumper stickers; business records; catalogs (documents); clippings (information artifacts); collages (visual works); color photographs; commercial correspondence; cue sheets; drawings (visual works); financial records; hardcover books; house organs; invoices; notes; paintings (visual works); pamphlets; photograph albums; picture postcards; posters; programs (documents); receipts (financial records); résumés (personnel records); screenplays; transcripts; transparencies; trophies (objects); videotapes
Related Collections
John P. Bradford papers.
Minnesota Historical Society Manuscript Collection http://www2.mnhs.org/library/findaids/00254.xml
Louis de Rochemont Collection
Keene State College College Archives & Special Collections, Wallace E. Mason Library http://commons.keene.edu/findingguides/26/
Life Around Us Archival Collection
HBO Archives http://www.hboarchives.com/apps/searchlibrary/ctl/marchoftime
The March of Time Archival Collection
HBO Archives http://www.hboarchives.com/apps/searchlibrary/ctl/marchoftime
Lutheran Film Associates Productions Martin Luther Publicity Program Files,, 1951-1960 1952-1956
Evangelical Lutheran Church in America Archives http://www.elca.org/Resources/Archives
Lutheran Film Associates Productions,Martin Luther Scripts, 1951-1954
Evangelical Lutheran Church in America Archives http://www.elca.org/Resources/Archives
Lutheran Film Associates Productions,Question 7 Publicity Program Files, 1961
Evangelical Lutheran Church in America Archives http://www.elca.org/Resources/Archives
Lutheran Film Associates Productions,Question 7 Publicity Program Files, 1961
Evangelical Lutheran Church in America Archives http://www.elca.org/Resources/Archives
Container List
- Series 1, Business Materials, 1933-1985
  Scope and Content
  Series comprises correspondence, memorandums, contracts, financial records, receipts, meeting minutes, résumés, employment applications, brochures, pamphlets, programs, film catalogs, business cards and other materials related to Wolff's career in film publicity and production. Materials date from 1933 through 1985. The series is further divided into three subseries. "Time, Inc./Time-Life" consists of business materials relating to Wolff's tenure as editor and associate producer at Time, Inc. (1936-1949) as well as later materials regarding Time-Life Films productions and The March of Time retrospectives. Subseries "Lutheran Film Associates" contains documents and records related to projects sponsored, produced or otherwise supported by that entity. Subseries "General" comprises the remainder of business-related materials in the collection, the amounts of which are considered to be too small to warrant division into any additional subseries, or pertain to Wolff's career as a whole rather than any single activity or organization.
  Arrangement
  Series materials are located in four boxes. Dated materials within each series folder are mostly arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Subseries 1,Time, Inc./Time-Life, 1968-1981
    - no title (Box C301)
      - Roy E. Larsen, April 24, 1976 (Folder 38)
        Letter from Roy E. Larsen, vice-chairman Time, Inc., board of directors, regarding The Joy of Bach, retirement party.
      - Description of Time Life Films, 1970 (Folder 76)
        Short history of Time-Life Films, dated 3/70.
    - no title (Box C309)
      - The March of Time Revisited -- Proposals, 1975 (Folder 7)
        Bound proposal, newspaper articles,The Best of March of Time, correspondence with Time-Life Films and Lurco Films Inc., and subject list. The date 1975 is found on a letter inside the proposal.
      - T/L Archives --March of Time, 1981 (Folder 9)
        Correspondence with Time, Inc., regarding The March of Time.
      - Screenings in Vienna ( 1982 ), Programs, etc., 1981-1982 (Folder 15)
        Correspondence with Time/Life and Franz Schwartz concerning screenings in Vienna, 1981-1982. Materials are in English and German.
      - [Three-ring loose-leaf binder labeled "March of Time I"], 1933-1948; 1979 (Folder 20)
        Correspondence with Louis and Richard de Rochemont,Eugene Ormandy; photographs of Wolff and March of Time personnel; programs and press books for March of Time productions The Story of the Vatican,We Are the Marines,Is Everybody Listening?,Opportunity... The Story of the Best Location in the Nation; newspaper clippings; newsletters. In English and French.
      - [Three-ring loose-leaf binder labeled "March of Time II"], 1936; 1940-1943 (Folder 21)
        Photographs of Wolff, Louis de Rochemont,March of Time production Norway in Revolt;J. Edgar Hoover portrait (signed); correspondence regarding Wolff's enlistment in the U.S. Coast Guard; memos and correspondence from Louis and Richard de Rochemont,Eugene Ormandy; newspaper clippings; sheet music for "Hail the United States Marines" from We Are the Marines, signed by composer Jack Shaindlin; materials congratulating Wolff on his U.S. citizenship; Time, Inc. 20th Anniversary gala program; Museum of Modern Art Film Library program for The Documentary Film 1922-1945.
    - no title (Box C314)
      - Time/Life Journal with Interview with Lothar Wolff, 1971 (Folder 30)
        8/6/1971 issue of Time, Inc., in-house newsletter F.Y.I., with correction letter from Wolff regarding an earlier F.Y.I. interview.
      - Time-Life Journal with article on Lothar Wolff, 1971 (Folder 31)
        11/12/1971 issue of Time, Inc., in-house newsletter F.Y.I.
      - Time-Life Journal Copy, 1969 (Folder 32)
        8/29/1969 issue of Time, Inc., in-house newsletter F.Y.I.[photocopy].
      - Copy of Time/Life Journal, Sept. 26, 1969 (Folder 33)
        9/26/1969 issue of Time, Inc., in-house newsletter F.Y.I.[photocopy].
      - Time/Life Journal Copy, Oct. 17, 1969 (Folder 34)
        10/17/1969 issue of Time, Inc., in-house newsletter F.Y.I. with schedule of lunch-hour screenings of The World We Live In, aka Life Around Us.
      - Table of Organization for Time-Life Films, 1973 (Folder 36)
        Company organizational chart.
      - News Release: "The Golden Eagle Awards to Time-Life Films, Veteran Filmmaker Lothar Wolff Is Honored,", 1971 (Folder 37)
        News release and ad copy.
      - Speech by Lothar Wolff, presented at KLZ, Denver, Nov. 11, 1969 on T/L Films (Folder 40)
        Text of speech about Time-Life Films.
      - Time/Life Messages, 1970-1971 (Folder 42)
        Two memos to Time-Life staff.
      - News Release on Lothar Woff’s Career by Time/Life, 1971 (Folder 43)
        Biography
      - Miscellaneous concerning Time/Life Films, 1968-1972 (Folder 44)
        Correspondence; memo regarding American Film Festival winners; newspaper clippings [in English, German].
  - Subseries 2,Lutheran Film Associates, 1978-1983
    - no title (Box C301)
      - Porter McKeever, 1983 (Folder 48)
        Correspondence among Wolff, Porter McKeever (Asia Society),Robert E. A. Lee(Lutheran Film Associates).
    - no title (Box C307)
      - News Releases concerning The Joy of Bach by Lutheran Film Associates, 1977-1978 (Folder 34)
        Press releases.
      - Correspondence with Lutheran Film Associates concerning The Joy of Bach, 1977-1978 (Folder 35)
        Correspondence includes proposal to The George Gund Foundation.
      - Lutheran Film Associates Meeting, April, 1978 (Folder 36)
        Agenda, meeting materials, budget, note to Wolff.
      - [Booklet titled "Everyman’s Bach: A TV Special for Christmas 1976"], 1975 (Folder 43)
        Comb-bound presentation outline of proposed TV special. Prepared for Lutheran Film Associates by Wolff,Robert E. A. Lee, et al.
      - [Booklet titled "The Current Popularity of Bach"], ca. 1975 (Folder 44)
        Comb-bound booklet includes photocopies of clippings reflecting the current popularity of Bach.
    - no title (Box C308)
      - Lutheran Film Associates-- Meetings -- Reports, 1978-1979 (Folder 1)
        Lutheran Film Associates Production and Distribution Committee meeting minutes, memos, meeting agendas, expense reports, progress reports, invoices, and correspondence, all related to the production and release of The Joy of Bach. Also includes Lutheran Film Associates Board of Trustees meeting minutes, a Joy of Bach shot list and treatment.
      - Lutheran Film Associates-- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1974-1979 (Folder 2)
        Correspondence regarding The Joy of Bach[mostly English, some German]; memos, including memos to/from Robert E. A. Lee; Wolff salary receipt;Elise Simon Goodman[production assistant] cover letter and resume.
      - Lutheran Film Associates-- Report from a Meeting, 1979 (Folder 3)
        Binder containing Lutheran Film Associates board of trustees meeting report dated 10/23/1979; correspondence; memos regarding distribution of Lutheran Film Associates materials, project proposals (including film-strip series), budgets, financial reports, etc.
      - Miscellaneous material and letters concerning Martin Luther, 1980 (Folder 4)
        Correspondence regarding a new Martin Luther film.
      - Robert A. Lee,Lutheran Council in the USA, 1980 (Folder 5)
        Correspondence from George Loft regarding Norwegians assisting Jews during WWII; a Dietrich Bonhoeffer film project.
      - L.F.A.-- Production Committee, 1978 (Folder 6)
        Correspondence; memo;Lutheran Film Associates Production and Distribution Committee meeting minutes dated April 26, 1978.
      - Lutheran Film Associates-- News Release for Martin Luther, 1954 (Folder 21)
        Press release.
    - no title (Box C367)
      - Miscellaneous Photographs, 1930-1960; 1971-1972; ca. 1983; undated (Folder 14)
        Black-and-white photographs of Wolff and Lutheran Film Associates president Paul C. Empie signing a Question 7 production contract, undated; Wolff and Robert E. A. Lee at a 1972 ceremony commemorating Question 7;.
    - no title (Box C368)
      - A Parade of Witnesses-- script, director Paul Lammers, 1983 (Folder 3)
        Script is in a blue three-ring binder titled "Luther Anniversary, Allan’s 8/19 draft." Also includes notes,Lutheran Film Associates correspondence, clippings, 1983 "Martin Luther Jubilee Festival" flyer.
      - A Parade of Witnesses-- Exposé by Allan Shore, 1982 (Folder 4)
        Exposé by Allan Shore, contains a proposal titled "The Hammer and the Pen" and related correspondence.
      - A Parade of Witnesses-- Script by Allan Shore, 1983 (Folder 5)
        Script with revisions and list of character names.
      - A Parade of Witnesses-- Misc. Correspondence, 1983 (Folder 6)
        Includes correspondence with the Lutheran Council in the USA,Luther College, and WGBH Educational Foundation.
      - A Parade of Witnesses-- Scripts, Notes, etc., 1982-1983 (Folder 7)
        Notes, working outline, proposals, correspondence, clippings, a speech delivered by Robert E. A. Lee.
      - A Parade of Witnesses-- Material and Articles on Martin Luther, 1982-1983 (Folder 8)
        Flyers, issue of National Geographic, brochures, and clippings.
      - Martin Luther, Jubilee -- A 500th Birthday Media Festival -- "The Hammer and the Pen,", 1983 (Folder 9)
        Worship Events Committee agenda; correspondence with the Lutheran Church of America and the Lutheran Council; television special proposal; "Martin Luther Jubilee -- A 500th Birthday Media Festival" proposal, including clippings, crew background, budget and "The Hammer and the Pen" outline.
      - Material on Martin Luther -- Letters, Newspaper Articles, 1965; 1982-1983 (Folder 10)
        Correspondence, newspaper articles, brochures, and pamphlets.
      - "Martin Luther": Treatment for a BBC Production, 1983 (Folder 11)
        Robert E. A. Lee shares a BBC treatment he received.
      - Miscellaneous for "Martin Luther" Special, 1979-1983 (Folder 12)
        Miscellaneous material for A Parade of Witnesses and past Martin Luther productions. Includes invoices, clippings, programs, outline and cue sheet, correspondence, notes, time-line, correspondence with the Lutheran Council in the USA, National Geographic Society, and Below the Line Productions.
      - Media Opportunities for the 500th Anniversary of the Birth of Martin Luther, ca. 1983 (Folder 14)
        Proposal for a "Martin Luther Jubilee" media festival commemorating Luther's 500th birthday. Includes outlines of A Parade of Witnesses, "The Hammer and the Pen."
  - Subseries 3, General, 1947-1985
    - no title (Box C301)
      - The Asia Society, July 12, 1976 (Folder 4)
        Letter from Phillips Talbot, President Asia Society, to Wolff regarding Wolff’s resignation as Chairman of the Indonesia Council.
      - Mark Scher(Asia Soc), 1978 (Folder 5)
        Brochure and correspondence regarding the Asia Society and Chinese films.
      - Bruce William Benenson, Résumé, ca. 1975 (Folder 6)
        Résumé of Bruce William Benenson with Variety review and New York Times ad for Benenson’s TV documentary The Marginal Way
      - Jürgen Bergs-- Curriculum Vitae, 1979 (Folder 7)
        5/17/1979 cover letter [in German] and résumé [in English] for film producer Jürgen Bergs.
      - Jack ?Black Elk Productions, 1979 (Folder 9)
        Correspondence
      - Leacock/Susan Woll Louise Brooks, 1981-1982 (Folder 12)
        Materials related to Richard Leacock and his film about Louise Brooks, including correspondence, clippings, and the full transcript of Leacock’s interview with Brooks.
      - Letters to Jacques Danois,United Nations Children Fund& Book by Donois:Les Moineaux de Saigon, ca. 1972 (Folder 14)
        Correspondence;"Wild Fruits" essay [photocopy]; perfect-bound paperback book Les Moineaux de Saigon by Jacques Danois.
      - Joost Van Rees; The Film Farm Inc., 1984 (Folder 15)
        July-August 1984 letter, handwritten notes regarding a phone bill.
      - Peter Nau-- Paul Fejos Publication, ca. 1979 (Folder 16)
        Correspondence;"Lothar Wolff über Paul Fejos" essay [in German].
      - Martin Neeb--Franciscan Communications Center, 1980 (Folder 17)
        Correspondence regarding "The Assisi Underground."
      - Stephen Garrett--Granada Television Ltd., 1980 (Folder 18)
        Correspondence regarding a documentary about newsreel films.
      - Concerning Appointment of Lothar Wolff with General Learning Corp., 1967 (Folder 19)
        Employment application, correspondence regarding employment.
      - Hugh Gibb, 1975-1985 (Folder 21)
        Correspondence with documentary filmmaker Hugh Gibb. Airmail letters, mailgrams, holiday card, U-matic tape labels and customs declaration for Gibb's film Rituals of Rice.
      - Hanseatic TV Prod.--Jurgen Voigt, 1977-1978 (Folder 23)
      - Robert Conte,HBO Manager, 1983 (Folder 24)
        Correspondence regarding Vera Wolff’s project "Rescue," a proposed film about the 1943 rescue of 7,000 Danish Jews from the Nazis; script for "Crying Time," a film about the after effects of Agent Orange
      - Hill & Knowlton, 1984 (Folder 25)
        Correspondence with Hill & Knowlton, public relations firm.
      - Pete Hopkinson:"The Screen of Change" planned book, 1978-1979 (Folder 27)
        Correspondence among Wolff,March of Time cameraman Peter Hopkinson, newsreel historian Ray Fielding.
      - Peter Horner, 1979 (Folder 28)
        Three letters.
      - Letter by Harald Wigankow; Ifage Filmproduktion with list of their productions, Dec. 11, 1974 (Folder 30)
        Letter [in German]; catalog of 16mm and 35mm films
      - Brooks Jones Bach DDR, 1983 (Folder 34)
        Letter from Brooks Jones to Wolff regarding Bach Tricentennial concert series.
      - Lazi Film--Horizon Communications, 1982 (Folder 40)
        Photocopies of two letters from Janine M.H. Selendy, co-chairman/president Horizon Communications, to Franzi Lazi and Heinz von Matthey regarding Stuttgart production facility.
      - Lazi Film--Frank Lazi, 1981-1983 (Folder 42)
        Correspondence between Franz Lazi and Wolff [in German, English].
      - Correspondence with Motion Picture Film Editors Guild, 1941-1948 (Folder 51)
        Materials and correspondence related to Wolff’s membership in the Screen Directors Guild and Motion Picture Film Editors Guild, including a withdrawal request from the latter due to potential "embarrassment".
      - Presho, Neville--Martello Films(Dublin, Ireland), 1976-1982 (Folder 53)
        Business card attached to accountant's letter regarding Export Sales Relief. Correspondence regarding Presho with RTE,Irish Film Board, and Wolff.
      - William S. Paley, CBS, 1979 (Folder 56)
        Letter [photocopy] from Wolff to William S. Paley (Chairman, CBS) regarding TV networks effort to "set some specific prime time for cultural programming aside."
      - Jere Patterson, 1982 (Folder 57)
        Letter of recommendation on behalf of Wolff;Patterson & Associates firm brochures attached
      - Michael Ambrosino,PB Associates Inc., Boston, 1979 (Folder 58)
        Correspondence regarding adapting existing European/Asian television programs about anthropology/archaeology for US broadcast.
      - John Phillips Yugoslavia, 1947-1948; 1977-1984 (Folder 59)
        Correspondence and articles regarding Life magazine photojournalist John Phillips and future TV projects based on his books Yugoslav Story and Jerusalem: A Will to Survive
      - Prof. Dr.Thomas Koebner--Philipps-Universität Marburg concerning the publication of History of Filmemigration, 1981-1984 (Folder 60)
        Correspondence between Professor Thomas Koebner and Wolff [in German]; lists of Q&A interview questions [in German] and separate lists of answers [in English], largely concerning Wolff’s career; two black-and-white group photographs featuring Wolff as a young man; 1930-64 feature film filmography.
      - Studio Hamburg Prod. Info, 1975; 1983 (Folder 70)
        Correspondence, 1975 price list.
      - Cal Thomas, 1981 (Folder 74)
        Handwritten letter.
      - Gerhard Trede Kompositionen (Composer), 1974-1980 (Folder 77)
        Correspondence with German composer Gerhard Trede [in German, English]; invoice.
      - Video Graphies Production, Letter by Jean-Paul Cassagnac, 1979 (Folder 79)
        Letter to Wolff.
      - Vigne/Jim Love, Portrait Logique d’Emma Barret, 1979 (Folder 80)
        Correspondence with French filmmaker Daniel Vigne and film distributor James A. Love [in English, French]; budget estimate.
      - West German TV ZDF(Dieter Franck), 1977-83 (Folder 82)
        Outline of "The World of the Thirties" documentary television series [in German, English]; correspondence; handwritten notes; directory for Hamburg 1977 German television programming fair.
      - Gisela Wolff--Matthias-Film, Stuttgart, 1979 (Folder 83)
        Correspondence [in German].
      - [Three-ring binder labeled "Bernard Mayes WGBH"], 1982-1984 (Folder 85)
        Correspondence with Bernard Mayes,Film Australia, regarding a Pacific Basin series; newspaper clippings; business cards; receipts; materials concerning Film Australia productions; "Some excerpts from my [Wolff's] curriculum vitae."
      - WQED The Joy of Mozart, 1976-1980 (Folder 86)
        Correspondence regarding a possible "Joy of Mozart" film; contract; consultancy arrangement; materials concerning films available from the Australian Film Commission;Metropolitan Pittsburgh Public Broadcasting pay stubs.
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1947-1984 (Folder 87)
        Times of Indonesia;Arne Sucksdorff;Matthew Fox;Museum of Modern Art,Paramount Pictures,Warner Bros.;Frank J. Ryan, "It Pays to Advertise Your Home Town" address before the Advertising Club of St. Louis, Mo.
- Series 2, Film/TV Projects, 1932-1986
  Series contains materials related to Mr. Wolff's produced and unproduced films and television projects. Materials date from 1940 through 1986 and include correspondence, project proposals, outlines, presentations, synopses, screenplays, script treatments, drafts, contracts, bills, invoices, expense reports, clippings, press releases, promotional materials, notes, meeting minutes, photographs, actors headshots, interview transcripts, screening reports, scrapbooks, Nielsen ratings charts, and documents regarding production and post-production facilities. Series is divided into 19 subseries according to project title, with a 20th subseries comprising materials related to miscellaneous projects. "Subseries 20,The World We Live In[aka Life Around Us]" is further subdivided into three sub-subseries, two containing materials related to two notable The World We Live In segments ("Rock-a-Bye Baby" and "The Not-So-Solid Earth") and a third comprising materials related to other segments or The World We Live In as a whole.
  Series materials are located in 22 boxes. If dated, materials within folders are arranged in reverse chronological order.